Phone: 617-901-6636 Email: <u>lalit.89@live.com</u> Webpage: <u>Website</u> / <u>LinkedIn</u>

International economist with expertise in empirical and quantitative research. Experienced in causal and statistical inference, structural modeling, technical writing, with additional skills in healthcare and financial analysis.

Professional Experience

Doctoral candidate, Department of Economics, Boston University (2016-present)

- Executed end-to-end projects in international economics, and macroeconomics, including research design, data collection, empirical analysis, and result interpretation.
- Applied causal inference methods in quasi-experimental settings including diff-in-diff, and instrumental variable.
- Developed and validated structural models of economic behavior to simulate changes in policies and technologies and predict changes in key economic outcomes.
- Quantified the impact of travel-costs on international trade using novel data and model and showed that easier
 access to visas can increase trade between EU and China by 1.3% and EU output by 0.43%.
- Identified a robust positive relationship between firm-size and information technology adoption using a unique factory-level panel data on computer and software equipment in India.
- Advanced training in demand estimation with discrete choice models, and forecasting using time-series methods.

Teaching fellow, Center for Data Science/Department of Economics, Boston University (2017-2018, 2021-present)

- Designed and delivered lectures for 3+ years on linear algebra, probability theory, optimization methods, and statistics and econometrics to over 500 students.
- Introduced fundamental concepts and tools in data science including GLMs, PCA, clustering, neural networks.
- Taught programming with Jupyter for Python, RMarkdown for R, and Stata for data processing and visualization, and econometric analysis.

Short term consultant, World Bank, Washington D.C. (Summer 2019)

• Proposed a new measurement of poverty using realistic household demand to account for non-food consumption; highlighted the relevance of price index with simulations.

Investment Banking analyst/associate, UBS-Verity Knowledge Solutions, India (2011-2014)

- Created detailed pitch decks for M&A advisory for the global healthcare markets, including market research, firm valuations, target screening, and due diligence; assisted the team that closed the \$7.3bn Coventry-Aetna merger.
- Communicated with clients, delivered on tight timelines, coordinated with team members, and mentored juniors.

Education

Ph.D. (Economics), Boston University, 2024 (Expected in December)

• Graduate student fellowship (2016-2022)

M.Sc. (Quantitative Economics), Indian Statistical Institute (New Delhi, India), 2016

• First class with distinction (76%); Merit scholarship (2015, top 5 position in the cohort).

B.Tech. (Biotechnology), National Institute of Technology (Warangal, India), 2011

• First class with distinction (8.46/10); Indian Academy of Science Summer Fellowship (2010)

Technical skills

- Scripting languages and statistical packages: Python, R, MATLAB, and Stata. Version control with GitHub.
- Documenting: LaTeX, Markdown, MS word and PowerPoint.
- Project management: Trello, Slack.